阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组
大家好 我是凯莉·安 欢迎来到计算机速成课
Hi, I'm Carrie Anne and welcome to CrashCourse Computer Science!
之前大部分课程的主题是硬件
So far, for most of this series, we've focused on hardware
即计算机的物理构成
- the physical components of computing
例如 电和电路 寄存器 RAM ALU CPU
things like: electricity and circuits, registers and RAM, ALUs and CPUs.
但是硬件编程既麻烦又不灵活
But programming at the hardware level is cumbersome and inflexible,
所以程序员需要更通用的编程方法
so programmers wanted a more versatile way to program computers
一种没“那么硬”的方式 没错 要讲软件啦！
what you might call a 'softer' medium. That's right, we're going to talk about Software!
第八集里 我们执行了一个简单的CPU程序
In episode 8, we walked through a simple program for the CPU we designed.
第一条执行的指令 即在内存0地址的是0010 1110
The very first instruction to be executed, the one at memory address 0, was 0010 1110.
之前说过 指令的前4位是操作码
As we discussed, the first four bits of an instruction is the operation code,
简称为OPCODE
or OPCODE for short.
我们假想的CPU中0010表示LOAD_A指令
On our hypothetical CPU, 0010 indicated a LOAD_A instruction
它把内存里的数值加载到寄存器A中
which moves a value from memory into Register A.
后4位定义了内存地址
The second set of four bits defines the memory location,
这个例子中 1110 是十进制的14
in this case, 1110, which is 14 in decimal.
所以这8位数字意思是“把地址14的数值加载到寄存器A”
So what these eight numbers really mean is 'LOAD Address 14 into Register A'.
我们刚才用了两种不同的语言
We're just using two different languages.
你可以类比英语和摩尔斯电码
You can think of it like English and Morse Code.
‘Hello’和‘.... . .-.. .-.. ---’意思一样——都是 你好
'Hello' and '.... . .-.. .-.. ---' mean the same thing - hello!
只是编码不同
they're just encoded differently.
英语和摩尔斯电码的复杂度不同
English and Morse Code also have different levels of complexity.
英语有26个字母的字母表和很多种发音
English has 26 different letters in its alphabet and way more possible sounds.
摩尔斯电码只有点和划
Morse only has dots and dashes.
但是他们传递同样的信息 而计算机语言也类似
But, they can convey the same information, and computer languages are similar.
我们知道 计算机硬件只能处理原始的二进制指令
As we've seen, computer hardware can only handle raw, binary instructions.
这是计算机处理器原生的语言
This is the 'language' computer processors natively speak.
实际也是他们唯一能理解的语言
In fact, it's the only language they're able to speak.
这叫做机器语言或机器码
It's called Machine Language or Machine Code.
计算机发展的早期 人们必须用机器码写整个程序
In the early days of computing, people had to write entire programs in machine code.
具体来说 他们先在纸上用英语写出高级的程序版本
More specifically, they'd first write a high-level version of a program on paper, in English,
比如‘从内存获取下一条销售额
for example 'retrieve the next sale from memory,
然后加到今日的总额中
then add this to the running total for the day,
然后周总额 年总额 接着计算税 等等’
week and year, then calculate any tax to be added... and so on.'
这种非正式 高层次的程序描述叫做伪代码
An informal, high-level description of a program like this is called Pseudo-Code.
当伪代码写完后 程序员再辛苦地扩展
Then, when the program was all figured out on paper, they'd painstakingly expand and
借助操作码表把程序手动翻译成机器码
translate it into binary machine code by hand, using things like opcode tables.
翻译完成后 程序就可以输入计算机运行了
After the translation was complete, the program could be fed into the computer and run.
想象得到 人们很快就受不了这个过程了
As you might imagine, people quickly got fed up with this process.
所以 20世纪40年代末到50年代初
So, by the late 1940s and into the 50s, programmers had developed
程序员开发了稍微高层次的语言 它更可读
slightly higher-level languages that were more human-readable.
操作码有了简单的名字 叫做助记码
Opcodes were given simple names, called mnemonics,
后面是操作数 形成指令
which were followed by operands, to form instructions.
这样不用再写二进制指令
So instead of having to write instructions as a bunch of 1's and 0's,
程序员可以写‘LOAD_A 14’这样的代码
programmers could write something like 'LOAD_A 14'.
我们在第8集使用了这个助记码 因为它很容易理解
We used this mnemonic in Episode 8 because it's so much easier to understand!
当然CPU不知道‘LOAD_A 14’是什么意思
Of course, a CPU has no idea what 'LOAD_A 14' is.
它不能理解文本语言 只能理解二进制数
It doesn't understand text-based language, only binary.
所以程序员想出了一个好点子
And so programmers came up with a clever trick.
他们写了可复用的辅助程序 这些程序可以读取文本指令
They created reusable helper programs, in binary, that read in text-based instructions,
自动地将它们汇编成对应的二进制指令
and assemble them into the corresponding binary instructions automatically.
这个程序叫做汇编器
This program is called - you guessed it - an Assembler.
它读取汇编语言写成的程序
It reads in a program written in an Assembly Language and converts it
并转换成原始的机器码
to native machine code.
‘LOAD_A 14’就是汇编指令的一个例子
'LOAD_A 14' is one example of an assembly instruction.
汇编器逐渐获得了新的特性使得编程越来越简单
Over time, Assemblers gained new features that made programming even easier.
一个巧妙的特性是自动计算跳转的地址
One nifty feature is automatically figuring out JUMP addresses.
这是第8集的示例程序
This was an example program I used in episode 8:
注意到JUMP_NEGATIVE指令跳到地址5
Notice how our JUMP_NEGATIVE instruction jumps to address 5,
而普通JUMP指令跳到地址2
and our regular JUMP goes to address 2.
问题在于如果我们在程序开头增加一些代码
The problem is, if we add more code to the beginning of this program,
所有的地址就会改变
all of the addresses would change.
更新程序会很麻烦
That's a huge pain if you ever want to update your program!
所以汇编器摈弃了原始的跳转地址
And so an assembler does away with raw jump addresses,
支持插入跳转转向的标记
and lets you insert little labels that can be jumped to.
当程序输入汇编器
When this program is passed into the assembler,
汇编器就计算出所有的跳转地址
it does the work of figuring out all of the jump addresses.
这样程序员就可以更专注于编程
Now the programmer can focus more on programming and
而不去管内部的实现机制
less on the underlying mechanics under the hood,
通过隐藏不必要的复杂过程构建更复杂的程序
enabling more sophisticated things to be built by hiding unnecessary complexity.
我们已经在课程里讲过很多次了
As we've done many times in this series,
又是一层的抽象
we're once again moving up another level of abstraction.
然而 即使有了精巧的汇编器特性 能够自动连接JUMP指令与标记
However, even with nifty assembler features like auto-linking JUMPs to labels,
汇编语言也只是机器码的简陋包装
Assembly Languages are still a thin veneer over machine code.
基本上每个汇编语言指令直接转换为一个对应机器码
In general, each assembly language instruction converts directly to
二者一一对应
a corresponding machine instruction - a one-to-one mapping -
所以它实际上绑定了底层硬件
so it's inherently tied to the underlying hardware.
汇编器让程序员不得不考虑
And the assembler still forces programmers to think about
用哪个寄存器/内存的位置
which registers and memory locations they will use.
万一你突然需要额外的数据
If you suddenly needed an extra value,
你就得修改很多代码
you might have to change a lot of code to fit it in.
看看思想泡泡
Let's go to the Thought Bubble.
格蕾丝·霍普博士解决了这个问题
This problem did not escape Dr. Grace Hopper.
【格蕾丝·霍普本课程在第2期中首次出场，这里是第二次出现】
作为美国海军军官 她是首批哈佛1号程序员
As a US naval officer, she was one of the first programmers
【格蕾丝·霍普，1906.12－1992.1，计算机科学家、美国海军准将，世界最早一批程
序员，她是Harvard Mark I上第一个专职程序员，创造了现代第一个编译器A-0 系统，
以及第一个高级商用计算机程序语言“COBOL”，被誉为“COBOL 之母”】
第2集说到过
on the Harvard Mark 1 computer, which we talked about in Episode 2.
哈佛1号是1944年完成的巨大机电式巨兽
This was a colossal, electro-mechanical beast completed in 1944
是盟军战争成就的一部分
as part of the allied war effort.
程序用打孔纸带储存再输入计算机
Programs were stored and fed into the computer on punched paper tape.
顺便一提 他们修补程序漏洞的方式是实实在在地
By the way, as you can see, they 'patched' some bugs in this program by literally
在纸带上打补丁堵上漏洞
putting patches of paper over the holes on the punch tape.
哈佛1号的指令集很简陋 甚至没有JUMP指令
The Mark 1's instruction set was so primitive, there weren't even JUMP instructions.
要实现循环操作的代码
To create code that repeated the same operation multiple times,
需要把打孔纸带两端粘起来 形成实体循环
you'd tape the two ends of the punched tape together, creating a physical loop.
换句话说 编程哈佛1号简直像噩梦一样
In other words, programming the Mark 1 was kind of a nightmare!
战后 霍普继续了计算机的前沿工作
After the war, Hopper continued to work at the forefront of computing.
为了释放计算机潜能 她设计了一个高级编程语言
To unleash the potential of computers, she designed a high-level programming language
叫做 算数语言版本0 简称为A-0
called 'Arithmetic Language Version 0', or A-0 for short.
汇编语言与机器语言之间有直接的一对一的映射
Assembly languages have direct, one-to-one mapping to machine instructions.
但是一行高级程序语言
But, a single line of a high-level programming language might result in
可能触发CPU执行几十条指令
dozens of instructions being executed by the CPU.
为了完成这个复杂转换 霍普在1952年完成了第一个编译器
To perform this complex translation, Hopper built the first compiler in 1952.
这个专用程序把编程语言的源代码
This is a specialized program that transforms 'source' code
转化成低级的语言
written in a programming language into a low-level language,
像是汇编语言或是二进制机器码这种CPU可以直接处理的语言
like assembly or the binary 'machine code' that the CPU can directly process.
谢谢思想泡泡
Thanks, Thought Bubble.
尽管霍普保证这让编程更容易
So, despite the promise of easier programming,
许多人并不相信
many people were skeptical of Hopper's idea.
她曾说 “我有一个可用的编译器 但是没人愿意尝试”
She once said, 'I had a running compiler and nobody would touch it.
“他们认真地告诉我 计算机只能做算数 不能运行程序”
they carefully told me, computers could only do arithmetic; they could not do programs.'
但是她的想法没错 很快更多人加入
But the idea was a good one, and soon many efforts were underway
努力设计新的编程语言 现在已经有几百种
to craft new programming languages - today there are hundreds!
可惜的是 A-0代码没有留存下来
Sadly, there are no surviving examples of A-0 code,
所以我们用一种现代编程语言Python举例
so we'll use Python, a modern programming language, as an example.
假设我们要相加两个数并储存结果
Let's say we want to add two numbers and save that value.
记住 在汇编码中 我们必须从内存获取数据
Remember, in assembly code, we had to fetch values from memory,
处理寄存器和其他的底层细节
deal with registers, and other low-level details.
但是同样的程序用Python写很简单
But this same program can be written in python like so:
注意不需要关注寄存器或是内存地址
Notice how there are no registers or memory locations to deal with -
这些由编译器管理
the compiler takes care of that stuff,
从许多底层的不必要的复杂细节抽象出来
abstracting away a lot of low-level and unnecessary complexity.
程序员只用抽象表示必需的内存地址
The programmer just creates abstractions for needed memory locations,
叫做变量 并给它们命名
known as variables, and gives them names.
我们把两个数字储存到命名后的变量里
So now we can just take our two numbers, store them in variables we give names to -
这里选择a和b 不过可以是任意的名字
in this case, I picked a and b but those variables could be anything -
接着相加两个数 把结果存到另一个变量c里
and then add those together, saving the result in c, another variable I created.
也许编译器内部分配寄存器A储存a的数值
It might be that the compiler assigns Register A under the hood to store the value in a,
但是我不需要知道
but I don't need to know about it!
眼不见 心不烦
Out of sight, out of mind!
这是重要的历史里程碑 可是A-0以及它之后的翻版都没有广泛使用
It was an important historical milestone, but A-0 and its later variants weren't widely used.
FORTRAN语言 全名为“公式翻译语言”
FORTRAN, derived from 'Formula Translation',
在几年后的1957年 由IBM发布
was released by IBM a few years later, in 1957,
统治了早期的计算机编程领域
and came to dominate early computer programming.
约翰·巴克斯 FORTRAN的项目主管 说到
John Backus, the FORTRAN project director, said:
我的很多成就来自于偷懒
'Much of my work has come from being lazy.
我不喜欢写程序 所以我研发了一套编程系统
I didn't like writing programs, and so ... I started work on a programming system
使得写程序更简单
to make it easier to write programs.'
你懂的 典型的懒人 他们总是创造自己的编程系统
You know, typical lazy person. They're always creating their own programming systems.
不管怎样 FORTRAN写的程序平均是
Anyway, on average, programs written in FORTRAN were 20 times shorter
手写的汇编码的二十分之一
than equivalent handwritten assembly code.
FORTRAN编译器则会翻译并扩展程序为机器码
Then the FORTRAN Compiler would translate and expand that into native machine code.
业界认为它的性能不如手写代码
The community was skeptical that the performance would be as good as hand written code,
但是事实上 这样程序员写代码可以更快更多
but the fact that programmers could write more code more quickly,
很划算
made it an easy choice economically:
计算时间略增 但编程时间剧减
trading a small increase in computation time for a significant decrease in programmer time.
当然 IBM是卖计算机的 所以一开始
Of course, IBM was in the business of selling computers, and so initially,
FORTRAN只能在IBM的计算机上编译和运行
FORTRAN code could only be compiled and run on IBM computers.
并且20世纪50年代绝大部分编程语言和编译器
And most programming languages and compilers of the 1950s
只能在某种计算机上运行
could only run on a single type of computer.
所以如果你升级计算机 通常就要重写所有的代码
So, if you upgraded your computer, you'd often have to re-write all the code too!
为了应对这个问题 行业 学术和政府的专家
In response, computer experts from industry, academia and government
在1959年创办了一个协会 数据系统语言委员会
formed a consortium in 1959 - the Committee on Data Systems Languages,
格蕾丝·霍普是顾问 指导开发
advised by our friend Grace Hopper - to guide the development of
不同机器通用的编程语言
a common programming language that could be used across different machines.
成果是高级易用的 通用商业语言
The result was the high-level, easy to use, Common Business-Oriented Language,
简称COBOL
or COBOL for short.
为了兼容不同的底层硬件
To deal with different underlying hardware,
每种计算机架构需要专用的COBOL编译器
each computing architecture needed its own COBOL compiler.
但是基本上这些编译器都能接受相同的COBOL源代码
But critically, these compilers could all accept the same COBOL source code,
不论编译器在哪种计算机运行
no matter what computer it was run on.
这个概念叫做一次编写 随处运行
This notion is called write once, run anywhere.
【write once, run anywhere 是SUN公司为宣传Java语言的跨平台性能而设计的口号】
今天的绝大多数编程语言都是这样
It's true of most programming languages today, a benefit of moving away from
不再依赖与CPU绑定的汇编语言和机器码
a benefit of moving away from assembly and machine code, which is still CPU specific.
这降低了计算机的使用门槛
The biggest impact of all this was reducing computing's barrier to entry.
高级语言出现之前
Before high level programming languages existed,
计算机是专家和爱好者的专属领域
it was a realm exclusive to computer experts and enthusiasts.
并且通常是他们的全职工作
And it was often their full time profession.
但是现在 科学家 工程师 医生 经济学家 教师 等等
But now, scientists, engineers, doctors, economists, teachers, and many others
都在工作中使用计算机
could incorporate computation into their work .
多亏了这些语言 计算机从一个繁琐且深奥的学科
Thanks to these languages, computing went from a cumbersome and esoteric discipline
变成了通用易用的工具
to a general purpose and accessible tool.
同时 编程宣传抽象使得计算机专家
At the same time, abstraction in programming allowed those computer experts -
现在叫做职业程序员 能够创造更加复杂高深的程序
now 'professional programmers' - to create increasingly sophisticated programs,
需要成百上千万甚至更多行的汇编代码来实现
which would have taken millions, tens of millions, or even more lines of assembly code.
编程语言的发展并未止步于1959年
Now, this history didn't end in 1959.
实际上设计编程语言的黄金时期才刚开始
In fact, a golden era in programming language design jump started,
计算机硬件也同步发生巨大的发展
evolving in lockstep with dramatic advances in computer hardware.
20世纪60年代 有ALGOL LISP BASIC 等语言
In the 1960s, we had languages like ALGOL, LISP and BASIC.
70年代发布了Pascal C Smalltalk
In the 70’s: Pascal, C and Smalltalk were released.
80年代产生了C++ Objective-C Perl
The 80's gave us C++, Objective-C, and Perl.
90年代有Python Ruby Java
And the 90's: python, ruby, and Java.
千禧年后诞生了 Swift C# Go
And the new millennium has seen the rise of Swift, C#, and Go
不要同Let it go（歌曲）和Pokeman Go（游戏） 混淆了
- not to be confused with Let it Go and Pokemon Go.
有些听上去很熟悉 很多至今还在用
Anyway, some of these might sound familiar - many are still around today.
你正在用的网页浏览器很可能
It's extremely likely that the web browser you're using right now
是用C++或Objective-C写的
was written in C++ or Objective-C.
我给的这些名单只是冰山一角
That list I just gave is the tip of the iceberg.
有高级新功能的语言不断出现
And languages with fancy, new features are proposed all the time.
每种语言都使用新的精巧抽象
Each new language attempts to leverage new and clever abstractions to
把编程的某方面变简单或是更强大
make some aspect of programming easier or more powerful,
或者利用新兴技术和平台
or take advantage of emerging technologies and platforms,
让人们可以更快地做到更加不可思议的事
so that more people can do more amazing things, more quickly.
很多人认为终极编程是使用日常英语
Many consider the holy grail of programming to be the use of  'plain ol' English',
你只要说出指令
where you can literally just speak what you want the computer to do,
计算机就会听懂并执行
it figures it out, and executes it.
这种智能系统目前只是科幻
This kind of intelligent system is science fiction… for now.
《2001：太空漫游》的粉丝可能会有这个期待
And fans of 2001: A Space Odyssey may be okay with that.
现在你知道了编程语言的知识
Now that you know all about programming languages,
接下来几集我们将要深入研究
we're going to deep dive for the next couple of episodes,
让你逐步理解编程语言及通过其编写的软件
and we'll continue to build your understanding of how programming languages,
如何完成难以置信的事情
and the software they create, are used to do cool and unbelievable things.
下周见
See you next week.
阿尔法小分队荣誉译制
翻：@ErrorEnvyEnchant 校：@Auriance 压制：@Mihael_Ho
长期招募 详情见微博置顶@阿尔法小分队科教组